For this third exercise, an object oriented programming, we're going to learn about classes
and self-instance variables, inheritance, and also using the IS subclass and IS instance methods
to learn a little bit more about our class structure.
This time around we're going to be making some files, so I'm going to make a new file and
I'm going to save it as classexample.py, just in the root here.
And we're going to practice making a simple class.
We're going to pass in several variables and then we're going to save them to the instance
by using self.
So we'll type class vehicle, define that dunder in it class, and what do I have to pass
to dunder in it?
Self.
Even if I accept no arguments, self always has to be there, but we will take a few arguments
we're going to take a make, a model, and the fuel is going to be gas.
And to save those values to our instance, we're going to have to do a self.make is equal
to make, self.model is equal to model, self.fuel is equal to fuel.
Okay, yesterday we talked about main methods and when we would want to put our code in
a main method, the distor reminder is not required.
So for these simple exercises, I'm just going to put the code where I use the class I defined
just right underneath here in the same file.
Just remember, indentation is important.
So this indentation level belongs to this method.
This indentation level where def is belongs to the class.
So if we're going to want to use this class, we're going to have to break out of that
class's indentation level.
And I'm going to say that my daily car is a vehicle, and it's a Subaru cross truck.
Okay, and let's take a look at what this prints out, too.
So remember the fastest way to run this in Python in DS code is just to say Python
run Python file in terminal.
And we see that.
Yeah, right.
It prints out that it's a vehicle object.
And you see this dundre main here.
We talked about why that is in the introduction class.
Can anyone remind me?
That gets set when we run this script directly.
So that's the same dundre main that you check for if you want to have a main method.
And this is a memory address, so nothing useful at all.
But we do have access to the variables.
And so I'm going to comment this out.
And instead, I'll print out an F string.
And I'll say, I drive daily.make daily.model.
It runs on daily.fuel.
Okay, if I run this, okay, a little bit of an improvement, right?
Because I drive a Subaru cross track and it runs on gas.
And I'll just put a period there to finish our sentence.
Remember that the better way of doing this is to create a repper or a stir.
So let's make a quick stir method here.
And it'll take a self.
Why don't we need to pass in any of the other arguments?
Make model fuel.
Sorry, you applied with them that self is attached to that.
Right, it's attached to the self.
It's attached to the instance.
So now I can, I'm just going to cut the string here and paste it here.
But this isn't going to work.
Why?
There's two problems.
I need to return it.
So it's a certain needs to return a string.
What's the other problem here?
Daily is not a scope, not a self instead of it.
Daily is out of scope.
We want self, so self.make, self.model, self.fuel.
Now, I'm going to uncomment my print daily.
And should see the same result.
So instead of having to conjure up this long string every time I want to represent my vehicle,
I can just use stir instead, and then it's in one place.
Okay, so we talked about class variables as well.
It enables that exist for all instances of that class, whether or not you, it exists
on the type as well as all instances of that class.
So you don't even have to have an instance to use it and see it.
So we're going to make a number of wheels, class variable here.
And I'm going to say four.
And now I can print out my daily.number of wheels.
And I'll just say this is the instance for the instance.
I can print out the class or type variable as well.
How do I access that class, not an instance, just the class?
That's right.
Capital V vehicle.
Okay, I'm going to run this.
See for the class it's four for the instance it's four.